yeah so metformin wise I think um
looking at you know checking out
somebody's hba1c is Al always going to
be helpful and looking at their General
metabolic risk profile um and uh looking
at their body composition as well um and
but it can help with those um obviously
it can help from if they've got an
elevated hb1c certainly if they're
drifting into the pre-diabetic range
um you want to be looking at all sort of
Lifestyle factors and what people's
diets are like because the other thing
is that
you want to be encouraging lifestyle
changes if they're appropriate rather
than medicating things
unnecessarily um and I think there are
there is quite a large group of patients
that come to trt having had a really
tough time of it over a really
protracted period of time um and kind of
using that to really examine and get
honest about your commitment towards
your health as well can be quite helpful
um and using that to you know start
looking at all elements of things um
also considering yes metformin does uh
you know can play a role with regards
the um management of metabolics um the
metabolic picture for some people who've
been struggling with this for a longer
period um but also putting together
actually if you're starting trt you
might might be starting HCG and tadalfil
and adding meformin into the mix you can
end up with you know um Felix mentioned
earlier on about the sort of the poly
Pharmacy element of things and throwing
drugs at a situation that might be
managed by diet and exercise that you
might find easier to do um can be an
extra you know it can be an amazing tool
don't get me wrong but it can be that
there were other things to try before
adding in met Foreman
um yeah think just to add to what to add
to what Angela is saying there like the
the the the main consensus of evidence
for met forming um is that it it does
appear to have uh sort of Health span
positive net benefits um but that's
usually or it's believe it's quite
controversial you can get people arguing
for and against the use of Metformin in
this manner um but it's been shown to
reduce um sort of the incidence rate or
severity of existing conditions like
diabetes um and uh C vascular disease
and cognitive decline and even certain
cancers if you look in the evidence um
but I I think that's all indirectly VI
its uh cellular metabolism uh modulating
properties and and it's um and that's
usually via enhancing enhancing insulin
sensitivity which then reduces your
weight which reduces oxidative stress
and therefore gives protective effects
from a cardiovascular point of view
particularly in the endenial lining of
blood vessels but it's all because
you're improving that person's body
habitus um not necessarily as a direct
result of the drug so I don't think in a
dose dependent manner having a higher
dose of Metformin will will increase
your health span by anything it will
actually just make you uh exercise more
eat better and then it has indirect
effects in insulin sensitivity but yeah
there there are there are for and
against like Angela was saying of trying
to keep Pharmacy simple um and then
actually finding a net benefit from a
drug yeah yeah and I I think like like I
said there are so many additional
benefits that you can get from starting
trt and normalizing your testosterone
with regards to moood with regards to
energy level um and actually people
often find that if they do you know if
they have been challenged with a body
habitus that isn't quite so healthy
often they find the motivation and they
get up and go to do the exercise and
start eating better and start doing a
bit of reflection whereas before they've
had so much brain fog about them that
they you know struggle to plan their
week around going to the gym and around
eating and things like that but actually
once they feel like they've been getting
the help that they need um it really
feels like things feel a little bit
easier to tackle like that so yeah I I I
think I would aim for lifestyle first
and it certainly wouldn't be something
that I started people off on if there
were weight management issues as well I
mean the other thing you could think
about would be um G1 Inhibitors and um
sort of uh semaglutide for example
potentially but again it wouldn't be a
starting point necessarily
[Music]